<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<chapter xml:id="chapter-hilbert-space-properties" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<title>Hilbert spaces: basic properties and examples (1.1)</title>


    <introduction>
        <p>This course assumes real analysis and topology (MAT 601, 701) but not complex analysis. If you did not take MAT 712, omit the example of Bergman spaces in section 1.1.  </p>
<p>Our overarching goal is to unleash the power of linear algebra and topology on spaces of functions. We will find that the <term>completeness</term> of such spaces is essential for our progress. The development of functional analysis was made possible by measure theory advances of early 20th century, which allowed us to define complete spaces of functions in terms of integrals.</p>
    </introduction>

<section xml:id="section-hilbert-spaces">
<title>Hilbert spaces definition and examples</title>

<p>By definition, a Hilbert space is a complete inner product space. We will unpack this statement step by step.</p>

<p>All our vector spaces are over <m>\mathbb R</m> or <m>\mathbb C</m>; let's make the convention it's <m>\mathbb C</m> unless stated otherwise. So, we can add things and multiply them by complex numbers. Some examples of such spaces:</p>

<p>All functions <m>f: [0,1]\to\mathbb C</m>. Or, all continuous functions. Or, all differentiable. Or integrable. </p>

<p>As a matter of fact, we could talk about functions <m>f:\Omega\to\mathbb C</m> where <m>\Omega</m> is a completely abstract set; then of course there is no continuity or differentiability.  If <m>\Omega</m> has <m>n</m> elements, this is an <m>n</m>-dimensional space, if infinite; it's infinite-dimensional. 
Sequences are just functions with <m>\Omega=\mathbb N</m>. It is often more convenient to retain the functional notation, writing elements of sequence <m>x</m> as <m>x(k)</m> instead of <m>x_k</m>. </p>

</section>

<section xml:id="subsection-hilbert-spaces-ip">
	<title>Inner product</title>

<p>An inner product gives the space geometry: we can talk about orthogonal vectors. Later it also gives the notion of norm, hence of metric. 
By definition the inner product <m>\inn{x,y}</m> is sesquilinear and positive.</p> 

<p>For finite-dimensional vector spaces, the standard inner product is <m>\sum_{k=1}^n x(k)\overline{y(k)}</m>. More generally, if there is a measure <m>\mu</m> on the space <m>\Omega</m>, we can do <m>\int_\Omega  x\overline{y}\,d\mu</m>. Special cases: <m>\Omega=[0, 1]</m> with the Lebesgue measure; <m>\Omega=\mathbb N</m> with counting measure. </p>

<p> We should be more careful with the last example because here because expressions like <m>\sum_{k=1}^\infty x(k)\overline{y(k)}</m> might not converge. One way to avoid this issue it by restricting the set of functions or sequences involved. A convenient example of an inner product space is <m>c_{00}</m> is the space of sequences <m>x:\mathbb N\to\mathbb C</m> such that the support <m>\{k: x(k)\ne 0\}</m> is finite. However, this is not a Hilbert space, as we will see soon. </p>

<p>A more sophisticated approach is to require <m>\sum |x(k)|^2 &lt; \infty</m>; this defines <m>\ell^2</m>, the canonical example of an infinite-dimensional Hilbert space. </p>

<p>More generally, given a measure space <m>\Omega</m> with a measure <m>\mu</m>, we can define the space
<m>L^2(\Omega)</m> as the set of equivalence classes of Lebesgue measurable functions <m>f\colon \Omega\to\mathbb C</m> such that <m>|f|^2</m> is integrable (<m>\int_\Omega |f|^2\,d\mu &lt; \infty</m> is finite). 
The unit interval with the Lebesgue measure is a standard example: <m>L^2([0, 1])</m>. 
</p>


</section>

<section xml:id="subsection-hilbert-spaces-norm">
	<title>Norm</title>

<p>In general, a norm is homogeneous, positive except at <m>0</m>, and satisfies the triangle inequality. 
An inner product induces a norm by <m>\|x\|=\sqrt{\inn{x,x}}</m>. The triangle inequality is not obvious, and for it we need the CBS inequalityin its abstract form <m>\abs{\inn{x,y}}\le \|x\| \|y\|</m>. Originally it was proved for sums, then for integrals. Often attributed to Cauchy-Schwarz, omitting Bunyakowsky.</p>

<p>Proof of CBS inequality: <m>0\le \inn{x+ty,x+ty}</m> for real <m>t</m> implies <m>\re \inn{x,y}\le \|x\|\|y\|</m>. Improved by rotating <m>x</m> by a unimodular scalar factor.</p>

</section>

<section xml:id="subsection-hilbert-spaces-converge">
	<title>Convergence and completeness</title>

<p>Metric gives us notion of convergence (and everything else: open, closed, compact sets...) In particular, we can ask whether the inner product space is <em>complete</em> (all Cauchy sequences converge). If it is, it's a Hilbert space. Functional analysis with spaces that are not complete is like  real analysis with only rational numbers.</p>

<p>Consider convergence in <m>\ell^2</m>. If <m>x_n\to x</m>, then for every  <m>k</m> <m>x_n(k)\to x(k)</m>. Not conversely. For example, let <m>x_n(k)=1/n</m> if <m>k\le n</m> and <m>0</m> otherwise. This converges pointwise to zero sequence, but not in the norm.</p> 

<p>An example of convergent sequence in <m>\ell^2</m>. Let <m>x_n(k)=1/\sqrt{k}</m> if <m>k\le n</m> (otherwise <m>0</m>). Then <m>\{x_n\}</m> converges   to
the sequence <m>x(k)=1/k</m> for all <m>k</m>. Indeed, <m>\|x-x_n\|^2 = \sum_{k>n}1/k^2\to 0</m>.  </p>

<p>As a consequence, <m>c_{00}</m> is not complete. </p>

</section>

<section xml:id="subsection-hilbert-spaces-completeness">
	<title>Proof of completeness</title>

<p>When proving that some metric space is complete, the following facts are useful.
<ol>
<li>If a Cauchy sequence has a convergent subsequence, then it converges.</li>
<li>Every Cauchy sequence <m>\{x_n\}</m> has a <q>geometric</q> subsequence <m>\{x_{n_k}\}</m>, meaning <m>d(x_{n_k}, x_{n_{k+1}})\le 2^{-k}</m> for all <m>k</m>.</li>
</ol> 
Therefore, it suffices to prove that every sequence <m>\{x_n\}</m> with the property <m>d(x_n, x_{n+1}) \le 2^{-n}</m> converges. </p>

<p>Given a sequence <m>\{x_n\}</m> in <m>\ell^2</m> with <m>\|x_n - x_{n+1}\| \le 2^{-n}</m>, we:
<ol>
<li> Show that it converges coordinate-wise to something (call it <m>x</m>), meaning <m>x_n(k)\to x(k)</m> for <m>k\in \mathbb N</m>. </li>
<li> Construct a dominating function (sequence) <m>z  = |x_1| + \sum_{n=1}^\infty |x_n-x_{n+1}|</m>. Here <m>z(k)</m> is finite and <m>|x_n(k)|\le |z(k)|</m> for every <m>n, k</m>. Consequently <m>|x(k)|\le |z(k)|</m>. </li>
<li> Prove that <m>z\in \ell^2</m>: this follows from the Monotone Convergence Theorem and the fact that the <m>\ell^2</m> norm of any partial sums in the definition of <m>z</m> is bounded by <m>\|x_1\|_2 + \sum_{n=1}^\infty 2^{-n} = \|x_1\|_2 + 1</m>.</li>
<li>Apply the Dominated Convergence Theorem: since <m>|x_n(k)-x(k)|^2 \to 0</m> for each coordinate <m>k</m>, and <m>|x_n(k)-x(k)|^2\le 4|z(k)|^2</m>, it follows that <m>\sum_k |x_n(k)-x(k)|^2 \to 0</m>. This means <m>\|x_n-x\|\to 0</m> as required.</li>
</ol>
</p>

<p>The proof of completeness of <m>L^2</m> is similar, with an extra step at the beginning: every Cauchy sequence in <m>L^2</m> is Cauchy in measure, and therefore has a subsequence converging almost everywhere (from MAT 701). We also have to pay some attention (but not much) to the fact that the elements of <m>L^2</m> are equivalence classes: in practice, one picks a representative of each equivalence class without saying this. </p> 

</section>


</chapter>
